<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse by Iohn Walsal, one of the preachers of Christ his Church in Canterburie. 5. October. 1578. And published at the earnest request of certeine godlie Londoners and others</title>
            <author>Walsall, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1578</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 108 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14690</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24995</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102702</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838472</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838472</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2853</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14690)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2853)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1121:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse by Iohn Walsal, one of the preachers of Christ his Church in Canterburie. 5. October. 1578. And published at the earnest request of certeine godlie Londoners and others</title>
                  <author>Walsall, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[84] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Henrie Middleton] for G. Byshop,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1578]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E F² .</note>
                  <note>Printer's name and publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Considerable print faded and show-through; pages marked and stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2853:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2853:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Sermon Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHED AT PAVLS Croſſe by Iohn Walſal, one <hi>of the Preachers of</hi> Chriſt his Church in Canter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urie. 5. October. 1578.</p>
            <p>And publiſhed at the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt requeſt of certeine godlie Londoners and others.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Neither is he that planteth, any thing, neither he that wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth, but God that giueth increaſe.</hi> 
               <bibl>1. Cor. 3. 7.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>AT LONDON. Printed for G. Byſhop.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2853:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2853:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT worſhipfull, vertuous, and his verie good Ladie, the Ladie ANNE BACON, <hi>Iohn Walſall</hi> hartily wiſheth mercy and peace from God our father, and from our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS my preſent at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and enterpriſe, will, perhaps miniſter vnto the reader dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cauſe of admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the one, by reaſon of the publiſhing, the other in the reſpect of the dedication of this ſimple and plaine diſcourſe. Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the firſt, albeit I may iuſtly depoſe, and call God to witneſſe that this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon is thus imprinted and made com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, not by any vaine deſire of mine, or terrene purpoſe in me, but at the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune ſuite of diuers godly men both of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Citie where it was preached, and of the Countrie where I inhabite: yet I am en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced openly to acknowledge that it is
<pb facs="tcp:2853:3"/> my bounden dutie of my ſelfe, without requeſt, euery way to ſeeke the glorie of my God, by exhorting priuately, by preaching publikely, by writing gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, to the verie vttermoſte of my power and abilitie. Howbeit, I am here conſtrayned humbly to bewraye myne owne infirmities, with heartie prayer for greater ſtrength. For mine own ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie and want of profounde know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, the aboundaunce of moſt learned volumes dayly ſet out, together with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of many curious heades and carping tongues, theſe ſo preuailed with my fleſh, as neither I could, of my ſelfe, be moued, nor by the importunitie of others, for a good ſpace, induced, to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe this treatiſe. But at length my wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keneſſe was ſomewhat ſtrengthened, and I perſuaded, not onely by the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of men, whome I haue good cauſe greatly to reuerence: but alſo by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirite of GOD, to collect this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon out of my notes, &amp; ſend it abroad, to the end, that, as by vttering thereof it pleaſed the LORD GOD mercifully to touch the heartes of ſome: ſo, by wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="tcp:2853:3"/> and imprinting thereof, it may like the ſame Lord as graciouſly to touch the heartes of many. So that my onely drift and purpoſe herein, is to ſeeke the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of our good God, by attempting, as he hath inhabled mee, to reclaime the wicked, to confirme the godlie, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerte the deceiued, to encourage the conuerted, that, as God hath created all, offered ſaluation to al, and nouriſhed vs all, ſo through his ſonne our Sauiour CHRIST, he may be glorified by vs al.</p>
            <p>This glorie of our God ought to bee of ſo precious and deare accounte with vs, that we ſhoulde directe whatſoeuer good thing wee haue to the aduaunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his glorie. This is not the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of carnall man, but of that moſte excellent doctour. IESVS CHRIST, and of his holy Apoſtle S. Paule. Chriſte the maiſter ſaith, <hi>First ſeeke the kingdome</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mar. 6. 33.</note> 
               <hi>of God and his righteouſneſſe, &amp;c:</hi> And Paule the ſeruant, ſpeaking of the Lord God, telleth vs, that, <hi>Of him, throughe him, and for him, are all thinges,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">Rom. 11. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6.</note> addeth, <hi>to him be glorie for euer: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi> Theſe and many the like ſcriptures
<pb facs="tcp:2853:4"/> teach vs that we are created, redeemed, ſanctified, and preſerued, yea, that all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lordes bleſſinges ſo without meaſure dayly powred vpon vs, tend to this end that his moſt glorious name maye bee continually extolled by vs. Both Moſes <note place="margin">Exo. 32. 32. Rom. 9. 3.</note> and Paul were ſo zealous for this glory, as they preferred the ſame to their own ſaluation. But alas, ſuch is the miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble condition of the world, that few are founde willing to take anye little paine, or to ſuſteine the ſhort diſpleaſure euen of the vileſt men, thereby to ſhewe their longing deſire of God his glorie. Men, of all ſortes, are made ſo drunken with their own vaine glorie, and in ſuch manner bende them ſelues to maintaine that ignominious and ſhamefull glorie, as in the meane time, the glorie of God is cared for, accounted of, and longed for, but of verie fewe, and as it were, of an handfull, in reſpecte of the huge multitude of ſo innumerable people. From this moſt impure and deadly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poyſoned fountaine of vaine glorie iſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Papiſtes glorious opinion of their meritorious workes, their proude
<pb facs="tcp:2853:4"/> conceipt of mans righteouſneſſe, their bloudie argumentes againſt iuſtification by faith, their obſtinate defences of moſt groſſe impieties, their daily coyning of newe counterfeit miracles for the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derpropping of their nowe falling king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. From this filthie puddle of vaine glorie ſpringeth the contemptuous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayning of ouermanie to ſubmitte their ſtiffe necks to the ſweet and eaſie yoke of Chriſte. Hence it is that the verie Angelles of GOD his Church, and true miniſters of his worde are ſternly frow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vppon, iniuriouſly thruſt to the walles, and handled vnreuerently, vnles with Popiſhe dirige, they will ſing, <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cebo:</hi> and as the Iewes willed Eſay, ſpeak <hi>Placentia:</hi> and with the Terentian Gna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. <note place="margin">Eſay. 30. 10.</note> 
               <hi>ait, aio: negat, nego:</hi> that is to ſay: vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they will with Iudas betray their maiſter Chriſte, and frame them ſelues to feede the ſinfull humours of carnall men, by wilfull neglecting the ſeuere commaundementes of Almightie God. Hence it is, that, if contempte of true religion, lothing of Chriſts holy Goſpel, countenauncing of the wicked, corme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranting
<pb facs="tcp:2853:5"/> of earthly thinges, carnall talke, vaine delectations, horrible blaſphemie, pride in apparell, epicuriſme in diet, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite in bargaining, vnchriſtian conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, if theſe, and the like enormities be reproued, and the terrible iudgemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of God denounced againſte them, vaine glorie will then be inflamed and ſet on fire with reuenging anger, and at daggers drawing with ſuch preachers. Thus I might proceede to prooue that vaine glorie doth euery way ſo abound, as the aduauncement of God his glory is lamentably neglected.</p>
            <p>Oh, that man had regenerate eyes to looke throughly vpon, and deepely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to himſelf, he ſhould then wel perceiue that no glorie, but all ſhame is due to him: he ſhoulde then be compelled to confeſſe, that whatſoeuer good thing he hath of the bodie or minde, the Lorde God hath there with adorned him, that he the authour therof might be glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with and for the ſame. Saint Paul to extinguiſh and quench out mans gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die thirſt of vain glory demaundeth of man this queſtion, <hi>What hast thou that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Cor 4. 7.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:2853:5"/> 
               <hi>thou haſt not receiued?</hi> To the ſame ende that vniuerſall ſpeach of Saint Iames <note place="margin">Iames. 1. 17</note> may be fitly applied. <hi>Euery good giuing and euery perfect gift is from aboue &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein the holy ghoſt teacheth that all the good things we enioy, either tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, or ſpirituall, they haue ſtreamed from the euerlaſting founteine of God his vnſpeakable liberalitie, that for and with the ſame we ſhoulde magnifie and praiſe his moſt glorious name. The Lord therefore in mercie graunt, that euery man, in his ſeuerall vocation, may ſo har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely bend all his affections, giftes, welth, wiſedome, worſhip, honour, or what ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer the Lorde hath bleſſed him withal, to the magnifying of him our moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and louing father, that euery one of vs may with a good conſcience and truly ſay with holy Dauid, <hi>Not vnto vs, ô Lorde, not vnto vs, but vnto thy name</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 155. 1.</note> 
               <hi>giue the glorie, &amp;c.</hi> And with Saint Paul, <hi>God forbid that I ſhould glory or reioice, but in the croſſe of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the world is crucified vnto me, and I vnto</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Galat. 6. 14.</note> 
               <hi>the worlde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thinke not (right Chriſtian Ladie)
<pb facs="tcp:2853:6"/> that theſe words are vttered ſo much to inſtruct you, as to enforme the reader of this letter vnto you. For by good expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience I haue comfortably found both in the right honorable my very good Lord your wiſe and louing houſ bande, and in your good Ladiſhip, his Godly and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient eſpouſe, ſuch care of Gods glorie in aduauncing true religion, in demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning your ſelues in the educatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of your children, in gouerning your family, in countenauncing of vertue and learning, in cheriſhing the poore and needie, as I might deſeruedly be deemed vnwiſe, if I had not obſerued it: careleſſe, if I did not remember it: vnthankefull, if vpon offred occaſion, I would not teſtifie it. But thanked be the king of eternal glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, this your care of GOD his glory is ſo vniuerſally knowne to the whole realme, &amp; ſo ioyfully acknowledge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Godly therein, that I neede not produce my ſelf for an experienced witnes of the ſame. Wherfore to conclude this branch, I will heartily offer vppe mine inceſſant prayers to the Lorde God, in the name of his ſonne our ſauiour CHRISTE,
<pb facs="tcp:2853:6"/> that both you, and all Chriſtians, may daily and continually growe not onely into ſuch contempt of vaine glory, and al vaine thinges: but alſo into ſuch loue and longing of his true glorie, and all heauenly things, as, in theſe euill dayes, ye may haue the ſure teſtimony of your owne conſciences, that you haue zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly ſought GOD his glory, and in the end, through Chriſt, be made partakers of his eternall glorie.</p>
            <p>As this care of Gods glorie hath drawen others to deſire, and me to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh this ſermon, which I truſt, will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent the vncharitable ſuſpicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of ſome, and ſtay the raſh tongues of others: ſo, me thinketh, I am to be blamed neither by you, nor of any other for dedicating the ſame to your Ladiſhippe. For, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding nothing be therin taught, which you haue not long ago learned, and nothing in ſuch manner deliuered by me, but hath ben and may be much bettered by others: yet your Ladiſhip, by peruſing thinges alreadie learned, ſhall not be altogether vnprofitably oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied, and at the leaſt this my fact ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:2853:7"/> make ſome outwarde ſhewe of mine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde heartie thankſgiuing for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits beſtowed vpon, and the truſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in me your humble and faithfull ſeruaunt.</p>
            <p>And when I conſidered, that by my Lorde and your La. I was firſt called from the vniuerſitie to teach your two ſonnes, (and thoſe ſuch children, as for the true feare of God, zealous affection to his word, obedience to their parents, reuerence to their ſuperiours, humility to their inferiours, loue to their inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, I neuer knewe any excell them) &amp; alſo that by the ſame meanes I was like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe firſt called from teaching of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, to enſtruct men, verely I coulde not but dedicate the firſt fruites of theſe my ſo generall labours to ſome of that houſe, whence I was firſt ſent out to be a poore labourer in the Lords great har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt. You ſhall here find no profounde learning, no exquiſite art, no curious eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, to delight your learned eares: but finde you ſhal the ſimple truth now imprinted as it was then vttered, to comfort your Chriſtian hearte. And I
<pb facs="tcp:2853:7"/> am throughly perſwaded, that as I haue the ſure warrant of Gods expreſſe worde for confirmation of the trueth herein conteined: ſo the holy ſpirite of God will in ſuch wiſe affect you with a like and loue thereof, that he will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel your heart to think, and your toung to ſay, Amen: Yea, and to confeſſe, that, albeit a ſinnefull man was the homely vtterer, yet the holy Ghoſt is the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted authour of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Nowe leaſt the portall ſhoulde be as great as the houſe, and the preface as long as the treatiſe, I will conclude and ceaſe from further troubling you. But, I truſt, not to ſurceaſe from hearty pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lord God ſo to deuor the harts of your good La. of your children and whole family with the holy fire of his heauenly ſpirite, that ye may <hi>dwell in his court, and be ſatiſfied with the pleaſure of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 65. 4.</note> 
               <hi>his houſe, euen of his holy temple: that the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 69. 9.</note> 
               <hi>zeale of the Lordes houſe may eate ye vp:</hi> that with good conſciences and ioyfull ſpirites, ye may truely ſay, <hi>ô Lord, I haue loued the habitacion of thy houſe, and the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 26. 8.</note> 
               <hi>place wher thine honour dwelleth:</hi> Finally,
<pb facs="tcp:2853:8"/> 
               <hi>that ye may be of that bright heauenly wheate, whiche ſhall bee gathered into the celeſtiall garner by the Lorde Ieſus, who, for euer, mightily protect, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully preſerue you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>At Eaſeling by Feuerſham in the Countie of Kent.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lad. heartie Orator, and humble ſeruant. Iohn walſall.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:2853:8"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>A SERMON preached at Pauls Croſſe by John Walſall, one of the preachers of Chriſts Church in CANTERBVRIE, the fifte of October.</hi> 1578.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Actes.</hi> 3.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <bibl>22</bibl> 
                  <hi>For Moſes ſayde vnto the Fathers, the Lorde your God ſhall rayſe vp vnto you a Prophet, of your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, like vnto me: yee ſhall heare him in all things, whatſoeuer he ſhall ſay vnto you.</hi>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>23</bibl> 
                  <hi>For it ſhall be that euery perſon which ſhall not heare that Prophet, ſhall be deſtroyed out of the people.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F (right honourable, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipful, and welbeloued in <note place="margin">Three things comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d this ſcripture.</note> our ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt) either the principall cauſe &amp; author of this ſcripture, or the inſtrumentes and ſeconde cauſes vttering the ſame, or the matters therein comprehended, if all, or any of theſe be duely conſidered of vs, we ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:2853:9"/> finde this preſent texte to bee of verie great authoritie, and fully repleniſhed with heauenly profite and comfort. Our cuſtome and manner is carefully to reſpect the authour both of wordes ſpoken, and déedes done: and as he is learned or ignoraunt, wiſe or fooliſhe, well affected or euill diſpoſed, ſo wée commonly receiue or reiect what ſoe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer procéedeth from him: for the moſt part ſtill meaſuring, in temporall thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, the matter by the man. I ſay in te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral things, bicauſe in matters ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, not ſo much the men that ſpeake, as the matters ſpoken, are to be regarded: according to that of our Sauiour. <hi>The</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 23. 2. 3</note> 
                  <hi>Scribes and Phariſes ſit in Moſes ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>. Al therefore whatſoeuer they bid you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, that obſerue and doe: but after their workes doe not: for they ſay and do not.</hi> But the authour of this ſcripture is of ſuch learning, wiſedome, holines, as we may ſafely, and are commaunded ſtreightly, not alone to credite and beleeue his wordes, but alſo to conforme and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion our ſelues after his workes. For as of all the ſacred Canonicall Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb facs="tcp:2853:9"/> ſo, of this nowe in hand, the holy Ghoſt, that ſpirite of truth, that comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 15. 26. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8 14. <hi>The holy ghoſt author of the Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Act.</hi> 28. 25. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16.</note> of the elect, that director of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the cauſe and authour. To this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd Paul in the laſte of the Actes, ſaith <hi>Well ſpake the holy ghoſt by Eſaias the Prophet, vnto our Fathers &amp;c.</hi> Againe, <hi>the whole ſcripture is giuen by inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God. &amp;c. Peter</hi> alſo in his ſecond epiſtle &amp; firſt cha. vttereth theſe wordes. <hi>Propheſie came not in olde time by the will of man: but holy men of God ſpake</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>as they were moued by the holy Ghoſt.</hi> In like maner the words ſpoken at the giuing out of the lawe, may truely be vnderſtanded of the whole body of all the holy ſcripture: to wit, <hi>God ſpake all</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>theſe wordes.</hi> Thus it is apparent and manifeſt of what reuerend and holy ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count both this, and all the ſacred ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ought to be, and with what hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie obedience we are to yelde ourſelues and ſtoup downe vnto it, ſith the holy ghoſt is authour of the ſame.</p>
               <p>If we likwiſe reſpect the inſtruments, whereby this ſcripture, as by certein ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond cauſes and meanes, hath bene deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered
<pb facs="tcp:2853:10"/> to vs, the excellencie thereof will <note place="margin">The preſent ſcripture vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by Moſes, Stephan, and Peter.</note> alſo comfortably and plainely apeare. For it is vttered by three excellente miniſters and ſeruauntes of the Lord, by Moſes the gouernour of Iſrael, by Stephan the martyr, &amp; by the Apoſtle S. Peter.</p>
               <p>Moſes as we reade in the booke cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Moſes. Deut.</hi> 18. 18.</note> Deuteronomie, and, as theſe two, Stephan and Peter doe witneſſe, was the firſt ſpeaker of this diuine ſentice, &amp; that by the inſpiration and direction of the holy Ghoſt: the occaſion whereof is alſo put down in that place of Deutero<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nomie, and conſiſteth in theſe two bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. Firſt, Moſes forbiddeth the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites <note place="margin">Againſt our Popiſh wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</note> to follow the impious maners of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heathen people, in vſing witcheraft, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceries, charming, ſoothſaying, in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing times and the fléeing of birdes: in making recourſe vnto, and aſking counſell of ſpirites and the deade: pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing all theſe abhominable vnto the Lord, &amp; the cauſe why the Lord hath rooted out thoſe nations, which were infected and defiled with theſe ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and damnable vanities. In the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:2853:10"/> branch Moſes chargeth the Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites to demeane themſelues with all duetifull and true harted obedience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord their God, ſaying, <hi>Thou</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 18. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhalt be vpright therefore with the lord thy God:</hi> thereby ſignifying, that, if we wil haue the lord to be our God, his mercies continued, his vengeaunce de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned, we muſt then not play the lame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>réeples, and hypocriticall halters by <note place="margin">Hipocriſie &amp; halting con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned.</note> making a mingle mangle &amp; hodgepoge of true religion, &amp; vile ſuperſtition: but we muſt go vprightly, &amp; become vnfeig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned deteſtoures of al impietie &amp; ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, and hartie zealous worſhippers of the Lord, according to that religion &amp; worſhip, which the Lord him ſelfe hath preſcribed and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded in his word. So that the drift of Moſes by this ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is to induce and perſuade the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſraell, and all true Chriſtians, not to depende vpon the vile and vaine illuſions either of ſathan, or of his wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <note place="margin">Wee muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend vpon, &amp; yelde our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues wholy vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the worde of God.</note> inſtruments, but to yelde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to the word of God, &amp; that with true, ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ie, &amp; through obodience. If y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lits had obiected to Moſes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the word of
<pb facs="tcp:2853:11"/> God was intricat and harde, Prophets to interprete the ſame were fewe, and <note place="margin">An obiection.</note> that Moſes and all the prophetes ſhould be taken from them by death, and ſo the worde of God coulde bee no ſuche ſure ſtaffe for them to truſt and leane vnto, Moſes, in this my text, doeth ſkilfully, and to their and our great comfort, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweare this obiection, ſaying: <hi>The lord</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">An anſwere of the ſame.</note> 
                  <hi>your God ſhall rayſe vp vnto you a Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phet, &amp;c,</hi> meaning that the Lorde will neuer ſuffer his Church to bée vtterly deſtitute of true Prophetes and faithful interpreters of his worde.</p>
               <p>The ſeconde inſtrument, whereby the holy Ghoſt hath vttered this ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the ſeconde by mine order, is Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan <note place="margin">Stephan.</note> the Martyr. For Stephan in hys notable Sermon ſealed with his bloud &amp; death, labouring to winne the Iewes vnto Chriſt, and to pul them from their <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 7. 2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> ſuperſtitious obſeruation of Moſes lawe, he maketh rehearſall of Moſes whole hiſtorie, as, of his byrth, of his caſting out, of his taking vp, and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing by Pharao his daughter, of his care ouer afflicted Iſrael, his killing of
<pb facs="tcp:2853:11"/> the Egyptian, his fléeing into the land of Madian, of the Angels appearing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him in a flame of fire, of the Lordes ſending him into Egipt, of the wonders done by his hand in the lande of Egipt. Leſt the Iewes ſhould be too ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly wedded to Moſes, and therby hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered from imbracing Chriſt, Stephan procéedeth, and ſubſtancially proueth, that, euen this their Moſes, whom they ſo loue, obey, maintaine and cleaue to, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen <note place="margin">Moſes and the law, teach and point vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſte.</note> that he in the lawe, and by his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice endeuoured to conduct and guyde them vnto Chriſt. This, ſaith Stepha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is that Moſes, which ſaid, vnto the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Actes.</hi> 7. 3</note> of Iſrael, <hi>A prophet ſhall the Lord your God raiſe vp vnto you, &amp;c.</hi> By which words it is euident that Moſes would not haue the Iews obſtinatly ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him for euer, but did propheſie and foretell of Ieſus Chriſt the Prince and head of all the prophets, the very mark wherevnto Moſes, the lawe, and all the Prophetes were directed: by whom a newe miniſterie, to wit, the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the Goſpell, ſhoulde bee publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed for the frée remiſſion of ſinnes.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2853:12"/>
               <p> Laſt of al this ſcripture is vſed by the Apoſtle S. Peter in this thirde of the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Peter. Actes.</hi> 3. 22. 23</note> Acts: Peter &amp; Iohn hauing in the name of Chriſt, that is ſay, by the vertue and <note place="margin">Chriſts name.</note> power of Chriſte, reſtoared him that was borne lame, vnto his lims: the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in woondering wiſe, ran vnto Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Iohn, accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting them the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of this miraculous eure. Herevp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, Peter toke direct occaſion to make an excellent ſermon, wherein he openly <note place="margin">Peters ſincere humilitie.</note> and with all humilitie acknowledgeth that this lame créeple was healed, not by their cunning, power, and holineſſe, but by the vertue of Ieſus Chriſt: he alſo vpbraideth them with the villanies done to Chriſt, ſetting before their eyes their betraying him, their denying of <hi>him the holy one and the Iuſt,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of a murtherer to bee giuen vnto <note place="margin">Peters ſharpe reprouing &amp; ſweet comfor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting the Iews.</note> them: their killinge of the <hi>Lorde of life.</hi> After hee had thus pearced their heartes with recitall of this barbarons crueltie, the rather to reclame &amp; bringe them to ſome déepe &amp; ſwéet féeling both of their owne ſinnes, and of God his mercies in Chriſt, he ſheweth that hee
<pb facs="tcp:2853:12"/> is not perſuaded they did theſe thinges wittingly, willingly, and of a ſet mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious purpoſe: but telleth them, that, after this manner, the Lord God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourmed that, whiche was long before ſpoken by the Prophetes. And therefore Peter exhorteth them vnto repentance, <note place="margin">True repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance fleeth vnto Chriſt.</note> and to turne vnto the Lord, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be done vnleſſe they apprehend and catch holde vpon Ieſus Chriſte the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed and perfourmed ſauiour, &amp; that with the ſtronge hand of a liuely faith. This doctrine was ſtraunge and odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the Iewes, who thought Moſes and Chriſt ſo repugnant, and the lawe and the Goſpell ſo contrarie, as, if they had embraced Chriſt and his Goſpell, <note place="margin">An obiection.</note> they would by and by haue reputed and taken themſelues for horrible ſchiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques and backſliders from Moſes and the lawe. Peter wiſely preuenteth this <note place="margin">An anſwere of the ſame.</note> obiection, by citinge this my preſent texte out of Deuteronomie, from the verie mouth and lawe of Moſes. By whiche teſtimonie ſo produced, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter doeth not onely declare his reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rende opinion conceiued of Moſes, but
<pb facs="tcp:2853:13"/> alſo firmlie proueth that his doctrine <note place="margin">The imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of Chriſt is no tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the lawe.</note> doth not diſſent from Moſes &amp; the lawe, ſith both Moſes and the law do, in theſe wordes propheſie of Chriſt which was then to come, and command obedience to be yelded vnto him at his comming, and that vppon paine of eternall ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine and deſtruction. As hitherto yee haue briefly hearde of this ſcriptures excellencie, in reſpect, firſt of the holy Ghoſt being author, and then of Moſes, Peter, &amp; Stephan vtterers of the ſame: ſo now (Chriſt willing) I will, in more ample maner diſcouer the dignitie and worthineſſe thereof, by reaſon of the matters therein comprehended.</p>
               <p>The whole matter doeth generally concerne the rayſing vp of a Prophete: <note place="margin">The matter of this text.</note> out of which generall head there plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly growe theſe foure particular and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peciall braunches.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Firſt, By whome, and for whom, this Prophet ſhall bee raiſed vp.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Secondly, what manner of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet this ſhall bee.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Thirdly, The attentiue eare and
<pb facs="tcp:2853:13"/> heartie obedience which muſt be yelded to this prophet.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Fourthly, The Puniſhment allot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſuch as will not ſo heare and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey this Prophet.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Lorde your God ſhall raiſe vp vnto you a prophet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is not vnknowen (right Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian <note place="margin">The raiſer vp of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete.</note> audience and dearely beloued in our Sauiour Chriſte) but vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally knowen, receaued and beléeued of all true Chriſtians, that, as the Lorde <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ephe.</hi> 1. 4.</note> GOD, before the foundations of the worlde were laide, did, in his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céeding ritch mercie, electe and chuſe <note place="margin">The me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of the church fore apointed.</note> vnto ſaluation a certaine number of mankinde, whereof his Church ſhould conſiſt and ſtand, ſo the ſame our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly father determined in his good time, and at his good pleaſure, to call thoſe his electe and choſen people vnto the true knowledge and comfortable féeling of his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, that ſo they might be iuſtified by fayth in him, and afterwarde glorified with him.
<pb facs="tcp:2853:14"/> Thus much Saint Paul teacheth vs in this ſhort ſentence, <hi>Whome he predeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinate,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 30.</note> 
                  <hi>them alſo he called, and whom he</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The preching of the worde the meane to call the elect.</note> 
                  <hi>called, them alſo he iuſtified, and whom he iuſtified, them alſo he glorified.</hi> For a meane, whereby theſe ſo elected might be called into the bodie and boſome of the Church: the Lorde hath mercifully giuen, and mightily preſerued his holy worde, wherein his will is reuealed, <note place="margin">Gods will is the perfect rule of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe.</note> which his will, is the verie perfect rule of righteouſneſſe, whereby the children of God are to frame and ſquare out the whole courſe of all their life, aſwell for true religion &amp; the righte worſhipping of him: as alſo for their conuerſation &amp; dealing in the worlde. To the ende this wil of God thus conteined in his word, might be manifeſted and made knowen both to the elect, for their calling vnto Chriſte: and alſo to the reprobate for their iuſter condemnation, to this end the Lord hath in his Church ordeined a miniſterie of his worde and will, and that by the meanes of men, to whome ſeuere commandment is giuen to ſhew the people their tranſgreſſions, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh <note place="margin">The office of Chriſts mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2853:14"/> the wicked of his way, to teach and baptiſe all nations, to preache the worde inſtantlie, in ſeaſon and out of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſa.</hi> 58. 1. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 33. 8. <hi>Math.</hi> 28 19. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 2. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 9.</note> ſeaſon: to exhorte with wholeſome doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, to improue them that ſay againſt it. And Moſes, in this place cited by Peter, aſſureth vs, that, as God, hath of his mercie, once ſet an inſtructing miniſterie in his Church: ſo with the ſame hee will euer bleſſe his Churche, ſo long as it ſhall bee militaunt and warfaring vpon the earth, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſtand in néede of miniſters. For <note place="margin">A comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble aſſurance of true mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the worde.</note> whereas Moſes ſayth, <hi>The Lorde your God ſhall rayſe vp vnto you a Prophet,</hi> He doeth vs to vnderſtande that God will continually ſtirre vp ſuch as ſhall diligently inſtruct his people in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true knowledge of his holy worde. So that this firſt entraunce into our preſent text, teacheth that the Miniſterie is no mans ordinance, but the Lordes inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution. To confirm this, many ſtrong &amp; <note place="margin">The miniſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery ordeined by God.</note> ſubſtanciall teſtimonies may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced out of the ſacred ſcriptures. For that Commiſſion <hi>Marc.</hi> 16. <hi>Goe ye into</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mark</hi> 26. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>all the worlde, and preach the goſpel to</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2853:15"/> 
                  <hi>euery creature.</hi> Thoſe wordes of Chriſt to the diſciples, <hi>As my father ſent me, ſo</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 20. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>ſende I you,</hi> that ſpeache of Paule, <hi>how ſhall they preache, except they be ſent?</hi> that reherſall of eccleſiaſticall functi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 15.</note> whiche Paule maketh, that charge <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 11.</note> giuen by our ſauiour, <hi>Wherefore pray the Lorde of the harueſt, that he woulde</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 9. 83.</note> 
                  <hi>thruſt out laborers into his harueſt:</hi> thoſe ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtarres in the right hand of Chriſt: <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Apo.</hi> 1. 16. 20</note> doe not al and euery one of theſe places ſtrongly proue that the miniſterie of the worde and ſacramentes is no fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of man, no inuention of fleſhe and bloude, no alone politique order for the gouernement of the common wealth, but the very holy ordinance of the Lord our God? Hence therefore ſpring theſe conſiderations touching the miniſtery, to witte.</p>
               <l>The reuerend care to be vſed in the Election and creation of miniſters.</l>
               <l>The conſcience and abilitie of ſuche as deſire the miniſterie.</l>
               <l>The account and eſtimation of the miniſterie.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2853:15"/>
               <p> If the Lord God be the authour of the miniſtery, then what men, of whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <note place="margin">What care is to be vſed in the election of miniſters.</note> countena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in the vniuerſal world, ſhall once dare with vnwaſhen hands, that is to ſay, of corrupt affection, to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect or admit any to the miniſterie, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the word of God alloweth not to be miniſters, and many times not to be ſo much as Chriſtians? If I haſtened not to other matter, I mighte in this place diſcouer the Romiſh Clergie, and ſhew both howe the holy ordinaunce and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the miniſterie is by them profaned, and how miſerablie they haue ſeduced the Lord his people: when as al <note place="margin">The popiſh Clergie no true mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt</note> their Prieſts are horrible Idolatours, and in moſt of them is found neither a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, nor will either to inſtruct and féede their flockes, or to explane and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen their owne Idolatrous ſeruice, or to make anie reckening of a right faith, and therefore I may iuſtly wipe that greazed generation out of the number of god his true miniſters. For in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of god it is neceſſarily required, that, as Paule writeth to Titus, <hi>they hold faſt that faithful word according to</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 9.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2853:16"/> 
                  <hi>doctrine, and be alſo able to exhorte with wholeſome doctrine, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince them that ſay againſt it.</hi> Sith the Romiſhe Cleargie are ſo farre of from imbracing, beléeuing, following, and teaching this faithfull worde, that they oppoſe and ſet them ſelues againſt it, with all their might and mayne, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane it, corrupt it, burne it, take on, and rage with fire and ſworde againſt it, howe then can they be accounted in the number of true miniſters? It may be that ſome will thinke to méete with me by and by, and to beate me <note place="margin">An obiection againſt ſome of our mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</note> with mine owne rodde: obiecting, that, if none bée true and good miniſters, but ſuch as are able and willing ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, without halting: ſincerely, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out corruption: valiauntly, without feare to deliuer the whole will of God conteined in his worde, vnto his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, then we ſhall finde in theſe dayes of ours, and in this our owne Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che many, that are no good miniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
               <p>It were a ſtraunge and lamentable <note place="margin">Anſwere to the ſame.</note> caſe, if in this age of our Church, ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:2853:16"/> groſſe imperfections ſhould be founde: and if ſuche bee founde, verely, rather teares are to bée ſhedde, and prayers powred out for ſpéedy reformation: then any long aunſwere made in this place to that former obiection. But this I muſt néeds ſay, that, as in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aboliſhing of poperie was attempted, fleſh and bloud might haue <note place="margin">Some cauſes of a maimed miniſterie in the beginning</note> pretended ſome reaſons for the placing of vnméete miniſters, namely, that the number of Popiſh ſacrificers to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placed, was great: the number of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned miniſters to ſuccéede them, was ſmall: the Vniuerſities were infected: as man might haue coulorablie preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted theſe cauſes of a rawe miniſterie in that beginning: So I knowe no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe worde of God, no ſounde autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of any writer, no good reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which can be now yelded for the continuance <note place="margin">No cauſe of the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance thereof.</note> and encreaſe of the ſame: eſpecially in this longing of the people to be taught, in this ſtaruing of ſoules with wante of teaching, in this comfortable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundaunce <note place="margin">Cauſes to the contrarie.</note> of able miniſters whiche both the Vniuerſities maye, and are
<pb facs="tcp:2853:17"/> willing yearely to ſende out into the Lordes great harueſt. Let vs all there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as many as wiſhe for the perfect beautie of Sion, heartily pray the Lord ſo thoroughly to deuour the heartes of all placed in authoritie with his grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſpirite, that both in making mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and in beſtowing liuings appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for miniſters, the glorie of God, the profite of the church, the inſtitution and deſcription of miniſters conteined in his worde, may alwaies be carefully &amp; obediently reſoected.</p>
               <p>Mée thinkes I ſée by his outwarde countenaunce, that ſome Romaniſtes heart is inwardly cheared with this my ſpeach of our miniſters. But ſoft a <note place="margin">No cauſe why any papiſt ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce at the former ſpeach of ſome of our miniſters.</note> while, looke before ye leape, and be not merrie without cauſe. For, bleſſed bee God, Englande hath at this time good and great cauſe ſpiritually to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce, and hartily to bleſſe and praiſe the Lord for the goodly ſtore of godly, lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, wiſe, &amp; painfull miniſters, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with <note place="margin">Our ioyfull plentie of good mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</note> he, in his rich mercie, thath ſo bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vs, as our forefathers, albeit, no doubt, they often wiſhed, yet they ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
<pb facs="tcp:2853:17"/> or neuer enioyed the like. And this I may boldly ſay, and proue it ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially, that the meaneſt of all our mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, though vnable to preach, are not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſuch, as for their true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, <note place="margin">Our ſimpleſt miniſters bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the beſt (if any be good) of the popiſh clergie</note> right worſhipping of God, zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous affection to the Goſpell, prayinge for and with their congregations in a knowen language, onely to the Lord, and their wiſhing well, and ſéeking, as they can, to doe good in their charges, &amp;c. may iuſtly bee preferred to the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedſt, to the wiſeſt, and deuouteſt of all that Romiſh rabble of ſacrificing prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes.</p>
               <p>As yee haue hearde that the Lorde God beeing authour of the miniſterie, therefore great care muſt be had in ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <note place="margin">The conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of ſuch as deſire the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie.</note> the dores of the miniſterie, that none, vpon any carnal reſpect, be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto admitted: ſo this conſideration, that the Lorde is the raiſer vp of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, the ordeiner of miniſters, the ſender foorth of preachers, ought ſo to preuaile in the hearte of euery priuate true Chriſtian man, that hee ſhoulde make choyſe rather to begge his bread,
<pb facs="tcp:2853:18"/> and abide any hard eſtate in the world, then, beeing vnfite for that function, to intrude himſelf into the ſame, either for a laſt refuge, or for eaſe, or for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, or anye other vnchriſtian conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</p>
               <p>It is ſaide in the Epiſtle to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brues, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 5. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>No man taketh honour to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but hee that is called of GOD, &amp;c.</hi> It is then Gods calling that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the office &amp; entring into the ſame, lawefull. Whoſoeuer therefore taketh <note place="margin">No man can aſſure himſelf that he is a true miniſter, vnleſſe he bee called of God</note> on him the office of a miniſter, without this inward calling of god, cannot haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſure teſtimony of a good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> he is a true miniſter. And how ſhal any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aſſure himſelfe that the Lorde hath cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him, to take the charge of his people to guide his flocke, to breake vnto their ſoules the bread of life, vnleſſe hee finde that the ſame Lorde hath mercifully adorned and beautified him with ſuch <note place="margin">How a mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſhall know if he be called of God.</note> graces, as are requiſite and neceſſarie for a miniſter of the worde: to witte, ſounde knowledge of the worde, abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſincerelie to teache it, ſtrongly to maintaine the trueth, valiauntly to
<pb facs="tcp:2853:18"/> conuince errour, and to applie thys worde with profite and diſcretion?</p>
               <p>This conſideration of theſe notes and markes, whereby the Lordes calling of any man to the miniſterie maye bee diſcerned, will, I truſt, teach men to holde themſelues thankefully conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with their owne vocations, and not to leape of from their ſtalles, and out of their ſhoppes and trades into the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie, to the offence of the godlie, the <note place="margin">What gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous offences ignorant mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters giue.</note> hardening of the wicked, the contempt of the worde, and diſpleaſure of the LORDE our GOD, which is the author of the miniſterie.</p>
               <p>Héere, according to promiſſe I woulde ſpeake of the dignitie and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of Chriſt his true miniſters, but that the ſame is ſo often and ſo plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mentioned in the holy worde of God, as no diligent reader or hearer of the <note place="margin">The dignitie of true mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, by.</note> worde, can bee ignorant of the ſame. The names whereby they are called, the office to them inioyned, the perſon they repreſent: all theſe euery one of theſe, &amp; diuers other reſpects to the ſame end, do plainly certifie vs of their high,
<pb facs="tcp:2853:19"/> holy and excellent function.</p>
               <p>They are called <hi>the ſalt of the earth,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Their names. Mat.</hi> 5. 13. 14. 1. <hi>Cor</hi> 5 1.</note> 
                  <hi>the light of the worlde, the miniſters of Chriſte, diſpoſers of the ſecretes of God, preachers of the worde, ſtarres,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 2. <hi>Apo.</hi> 1. 16. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>Angels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Their office is to ſeaſon and poulder the heartes of the elect with the ſwéete ſauour of Ieſus Chriſt their ſauiour, to <note place="margin">Their office.</note> be meanes to illuminate and lighten our darke vnderſtanding by a ſincere interpretation of the worde, to mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the Goſpell and ſacramentes of Chriſt, to receiue light fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ieſus Chriſt the Sunne of righteouſnes, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueigh the ſame to vs for the guiding of our ſteppes: to carie, like truſtie Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours, and faithfull meſſengers, the Lorde his will and pleaſure to his ſeruaunts. They repreſent y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> verie per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Lorde Ieſus, as is euident by <note place="margin">
                     <hi>The perſon thei repreſent Mat.</hi> 10. 40. <hi>Luc.</hi> 10. 16.</note> his owne wordes, <hi>He that receiueth you receiueth me:</hi> &amp; again, <hi>He y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> heareth you, heareth me: &amp; he that diſpiſeth you, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeth mee, &amp;c.</hi> Theſe fewe, but yet greate thinges ſpoken of the worthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Chriſte his miniſters, are, I
<pb facs="tcp:2853:19"/> truſt, ſufficient to bringe them out of that contempt wherevnto they are gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen <note place="margin">The conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt of godly mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</note> by the malice of Sathan, by the wicked practiſes of his inſtrumentes, and by the horrible vnthankefulneſſe of the worlde.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>THE SECOND PART.</head>
               <p>AS ye haue heard in the firſt parte <note place="margin">What maner of Prophete this is.</note> that the Lord ſhal raiſe vp this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete, whereby hath béen declared, that, not carnall man, but the immortall and euerliuing God is authour of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie, ſo in the ſecond place we are to conſider what manner of Prophete the Lorde ſhall raiſe vp: our text ſaith.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Prophet of your brethren, like to mee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wée reade in the holy ſcriptures of <note place="margin">Three kindes of prophetes. Marlor. loc. com.</note> three ſortes and kindes of Prophetes. The firſt are ſuch, as were extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilie ſtirred vp by the LORDE, and vſed to aſke counſell of the Lorde for the comfort of the Churche in her great
<pb facs="tcp:2853:20"/> extremities. Theſe Prophets were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Séers, of whom it is ſpoken in the <note place="margin">Seers.</note> firſte booke of the Cronicles, as of God, Dauids Séer: and of Samuell the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 21. 9. 26. 28.</note> The ſeconde ſorte were alſo extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarily ſente by the Lorde too inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prete <note place="margin">Interpreters of the lawe.</note> the lawe of God, when the prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes ceaſed, ſuch were Iſay? Ieremie, &amp;c. The thirde kinde of Prophetes are ſuch as the Lorde hath bleſſed with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie <note place="margin">To propheſie.</note> and giftes to enterprete and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie the holie ſcriptures: ſo that to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie, <note place="margin">Preachers of the worde.</note> or to bee a Prophete in this laſt ſence, is to open the worde of GOD by a ſounde, diligent, playne, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full interpretation, and to applie the ſame both for the ingendring, encreaſe, and confirmation of faith: and alſo for the reformation and amendement of life, ſuch, as ſome thinke were the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Actes.</hi> 13. 1.</note> at Antiochia, ſpoken of in the thirtéenth of the Actes. In this ſence all true preachers are prophets. Thus lik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 29. 18.</note> I take Salomons ſaying, <hi>Where</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The neceſſitie of Preaching.</note> 
                  <hi>Propheſie fayleth, the people periſhe,</hi> that is, where there is not a faithfull miniſtery, a true &amp; diligent interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb facs="tcp:2853:20"/> a through application of the word, there the people by heapes, runne head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into vtter deſtruction.</p>
               <p>To this ende, and in this meaninge doeth Moſes vtter theſe wordes, <hi>The Lord your God ſhall rayſe vp vnto you a Prophete,</hi> ſignifying a continuall mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie of the worde for inlarginge the kingdome, &amp; building vp the church of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Howbeit both Stephan in the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth, and Peter in the thirde of the Actes, doe ſo vſe the teſtimonie of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, <note place="margin">Stephan and Peter aplie this text chef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to Chriſt.</note> that they doe more particularly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreigne the ſame vnto our Sauiour Chriſte. For their purpoſe is to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade the Iewes, that to hearken vnto, and beleeue in Chriſt, is not repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nante and contrarie to the Lawe of Moſes, becauſe Moſes him ſelfe ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Chriſt, ſayth, <hi>A Prophete ſhall the Lorde &amp;c.</hi> There is no contrarie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie betwéene my firſt interpretation of this prophet for all the miniſterie, and <note place="margin">This prophet importeth Chriſt and all his miniſters.</note> my thus vnderſtandinge of Chriſte by this Prophete. For as this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete doeth generally importe the
<pb facs="tcp:2853:21"/> whole number of true miniſters, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, and preachers: ſo it hath alſo <note place="margin">Chriſt the marke of all true miniſters</note> an eſpeciall relation vnto Ieſus Chriſt, the head and prince, the butte &amp; marke, the ſcope &amp; end of all the true miniſtery, which euer was, is preſently, or ſhall be hereafter vpon the whole face of the earth. Beholde here then the comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſignification, and importaunte <note place="margin">The comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſigne of this prophet.</note> nature of this prophete, euen that Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, by his might and mercie, ſhall euer bee with his Church: and that, from time to time the Lorde will rayſe vp and ſende out true miniſters for his Church. This alone conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and knowledge is fully fraught with ſingular comforte. If we call to our remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that an houſhold with <note place="margin">The wofull eſtate of the Church wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting true mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</note> out a ſtewarde, waxeth diſordered: that ſchollers wanting an inſtructour, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be learned: that a ſhippe deſtitute of a guide is vnlikely to be preſerued: we ſhall then eaſily perceiue, and clearely ſée the moſte lamentable eſtate of the Church when it is depriued of true mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, which are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords ſtewards, to <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 1. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 19.</note> diſpoſe his ſecretes: the Lords ſcholma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<pb facs="tcp:2853:21"/> to teach his people: the Lords vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derguides to direct his flock of Shéep in <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 10. 16.</note> to the ſheepefold of Ieſus Chriſte. The faithfull among all other griefes, rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon this for one of the greateſt, <hi>we ſee not our ſagnes, there is not one Prophet</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 74. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>more.</hi> But, although for our ſinnes, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude, contempt, and diſobedience, the Lorde, in his diſpleaſure, doth often take away his worde, and miniſters, in ſuch ſort, as the worlde many times iudgeth the worde vtterly abandoned, and the miniſters thereof altogether deſtroyed: yet, euen in thoſe times of hott afflictions, the Lord hath continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally raiſed vp true prophetes and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, <note place="margin">God leaueth not his church deſtitute of miniſters in perſecution.</note> to his true hearted Iſraelites, whereof this Citie hath often had moſt comfortable triall &amp; experience. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, let vs faithfully holde in our harts as a ſure ground, and infallible princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for euer, that, if wee wil be diligent hearers, faithfull beleeuers, and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent practizers of his worde, <hi>The Lorde our God ſhall raiſe vp a Prophet vnto vs,</hi> that is, will ſtill mercifully bleſſe vs with the preſence of Ieſus Chriſte, and
<pb facs="tcp:2853:22"/> with ſincere, learned, painfull, diſcréete, and godly interpreters &amp; miniſters of his worde.</p>
               <p>Moſes procéedeth in the deſcription of this Prophet, and ſayth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>of your brethren, like to me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ye haue alreadie heard that Moſes ſpeaketh theſe words in generall man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner reſpecting both Chriſte and his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, but that Peter doth more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly applie them vnto Chriſte, and therfore it behoueth me to ſpeake of the ſame wordes.</p>
               <l>Firſt, as they generally concerne the whole miniſterie.</l>
               <l>The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they eſpecially touch Chriſt.</l>
               <p>To preſerue and keepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iſraelites, &amp; in them, all Chriſtians, from béeing <note place="margin">How theſe wordes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the whole mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie.</note> defiled with the impious maners of the gentiles, &amp; to make them for euer who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cleaue to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of God, Moſes hath promiſed a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinual opening of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word, &amp; wil of god therin compriſed. The peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple might haue ſaid to Moſes, peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <note place="margin">An obiection</note> thy meaning is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Lord himſelf will teach vs in his owne perſon. But this wee canne in no wiſe brooke. For,
<pb facs="tcp:2853:22"/> we founde his maieſtie ſo glorious, his <note place="margin">The maieſtie of God.</note> voice ſo terrible, his words ſo pearcing, at the giuing out of the lawe vppon <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 19. 18.</note> mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Sinai, that we looked for preſent <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deu</hi> 20. 18. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> death; and therefore prayed that wee might no more heare the Lorde ſpeake vnto vs in his owne perſon. Moſes, to take away this feare, telleth them that <note place="margin">An aunſwere to that obiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> this prophet <hi>ſhall be of their owne bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren;</hi> that is, of their owne ſtocke, bloude, and kinred: <hi>and like to him,</hi> that is, a man as he is, in companie with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as he is, teaching them as familiarly, as plainely, as mildely, as louingly, as he doth. Hence we are taught y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as it is <note place="margin">The good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God in teaching vs by our bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thren.</note> a great benifit to be rightly inſtructed in the will and way of the Lorde: ſo the Lorde hath dealt gratiouſly with vs, in that he teachech vs not in his glorious maieſtie, to confounde vs: but in his great mercie, to ſaue vs: not fearefully, by thundring, lightening, &amp; tempeſts to afraie vs, but by men of our own coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, of our own nature, of our own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintaunce, to encourage aad allure vs. <note place="margin">Howe this ſpeach touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Chriſt.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Now, to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d this ſpeach of Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:2853:23"/> (as Stephan and Peter doe) it muſt be thus conſtrued, that Chriſt, touching <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 22. 18.</note> his humane nature, ſhoulde deſcende from the ſtocke of Abraham, and bee borne among the Iewes. And therefore ther was no cauſe at al why the Iewes ſhoulde either feare or diſpiſe Chriſte, ſith by byrth he ſhoulde bee their owne countrieman, and in familiar, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing inſtruction, like to Moſes. But this Chriſtes likeneſſe to Moſes muſt <note place="margin">Chriſt not ſo like Moſes, but that hee farre paſſeth Moſes.</note> not be ſo taken, as if in Chriſte there coulde bee founde nothing more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent then was in Moſes. For, Moſes was but a man, Chriſt, God and man: Moſes was a man ſubiect to ſinne, Chriſt is a man frée from ſinne: Moſes was but a ſeruant, Chriſt is the Lorde and Maiſter. But Chriſte and Moſes <note place="margin">Wherein Chriſtes like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to Moſes doth ſtand.</note> are herein like, bicauſe they were both Prophets and interpreters of God his will to his people, &amp; becauſe Moſes was a liuely figure of Chriſt, as may appear by a briefe compariſon made betwéene Chriſt and Moſes. Moſes, being in cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite in king Pharaho his houſe, choſe rather to ſuffer afflictions with his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren
<pb facs="tcp:2853:23"/> the Iſraelites, then to liue in <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 2. 11.</note> eaſe and eſtimation in the Courte of Pharaho: Our ſauiour Chriſt, being in the glorious heauens, the ſecond perſon <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke.</hi> 2. 11. 12</note> in Trinitie, had ſuche compaſſion on our moſt miſerable eſtate, that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended and came downe into this vale of myſerie for the accompliſhment of our redemption. Moſes was vnkindly <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Nu.</hi> 12. 1 14 2</note> entreated of his brethren the Iewes, Chriſt comming among his owne, was <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 1. 11.</note> not receiued. Moſes deliuered Iſraell <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 14. 27.</note> from Egypt, and drowned Pharaho &amp; his hoſte in the red ſea: Chriſte raunſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vs from ſpiritual Egypt, which is <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 13. 2. 15.</note> hel: and from ſpiritual Pharaho, which is the diuell. Moſes fedde the Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 16. 15.</note> with Manna from heauen: Chriſt nouriſheth vs with his body and bloud. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 26 26.</note> Moſes tolde the people ſo muche of the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>The ſcripture conteineth all things neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie to our ſaluation. Luc.</hi> 16. 29. <hi>Ephe</hi> 2 20. 2. <hi>Tim</hi> 3. 15.</note> Lords will as was néedeful for them to know: Chriſt hath left writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred volume of the holy canonical ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, whatſoeuer is neceſſary to oure ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I might co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue this compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but thus much is ſufficient to ſhewe the reaſon of Moſes ſpeach: and thus we
<pb facs="tcp:2853:24"/> percieue how theſe words <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Prophet of your brethren like to me,</hi> may well be vnderſtanded both of all the miniſterie in generall, and of our ſauiour Chriſte eſpecially, and of each and of both, to our verie greate comforte, and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to become carefull and effectuall hearers of Chriſt and his miniſters.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>The third part.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ye ſhall heare him in all thinges what ſoeuer he ſhall ſay vnto you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>THe former ſcripture before handled, hath certified vs that God ſhall ſtir vp this prophet, and that he is therfore authour of the miniſterie: and alſo that by this Prophet, Ieſus Chriſte, and, in him, all his true miniſters are vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanded. Nowe theſe words conteining <note place="margin">What eare &amp; obedience muſt be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to this Prophet.</note> the third parte, doe vs to vnderſtand of the eare which muſt be giuen, and the obedience which muſt be yelded to this Prophet, <hi>Ye ſhall heare him in al things &amp;c.</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, ye ſhal with al obedience conforme your ſelues to his doctrine.
<pb facs="tcp:2853:24"/> Here Peter proueth that Moſes attem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not to tie the Iewes vnto the lawe for euer, but that the office of Moſes and the Lawe was to bring them vnto Chriſte. So Paule writing vnto the Galathians, ſaith: <hi>The lawe was our Scholemaiſter, to bring vs vnto Chriſte,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gala.</hi> 3. 24. 25</note> 
                  <hi>that wee mighte bee made righteous by faith: but after this faith is come, we ar no longer vnder a Scholemaiſter.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <note place="margin">The office of the Law is to bring vs vnto Chriſt.</note> it is plaine that the lawe canne claime no longer righte in vs, or rule ouer vs, after it hath once brought vs vnto our ſauiour Ieſus Chriſte. The ſcholler is in ſubiection to his ſchole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maiſter, till he become learned, and then he is ſet at libertie. In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the law hath perfourmed the office therunto appointed, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by it we haue learned to ſée and knowe, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge our infirmities, corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſinful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, vnrighteouſnes, &amp; to fly vnto Chriſt to be iuſtified by faith in him Sith this Chriſt, which is the marke whereat the law ſhooteth, and the iuſtifier of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous, ſith he is come, Peter, out of the law, exhorteth the Iewes, &amp; vs al, to
<pb facs="tcp:2853:25"/> heare him with heartie obedience. Yea, the glorious voyce of almightie God <note place="margin">Chriſt our a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone Schole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter.</note> ſounding from heauen, appointeth this the only Meſſias to be our onely ſchole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter, and vs to be his onely ſchollers, ſaying, <hi>This is that my beloued ſonne, in whome I am well pleaſed: heare him.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 17. 5.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Here we muſt make a diſtinction <note place="margin">Two ſortes of hearing.</note> of hearing Chriſt and his worde. There is one kinde of hearing which is onely externall and outward, when as the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone ſounde and voice of the goſpell oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupieth the eares of man, but entreth <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hearing that is only exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal to damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Eſa.</hi> 6. 9. <hi>Math.</hi> 13. 14.</note> not into the heart, there to take good &amp; comfortable effect. Of this hearing E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſai ſpeaketh in the 6. chapter, which our ſauiour citeth in the 13. of Matthew, <hi>By hearing ye ſhall heare, and not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand:</hi> Wher the Prophet, in the perſon and name of the Lord God manaceth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked, that, through their own malice their hearts ſhal be ſo hardened, as they ſhall onely heare the outward ſounde of the worde to their condemnation: but it ſhall not ſwéetely touche their heartes for their conuerſion &amp; ſaluation. Such hearers were traiterous Iudas, the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate
<pb facs="tcp:2853:25"/> Phariſes, the malitious wicked <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 16.</note> ones, to whom the preaching of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell is the ſauour of death vnto death.</p>
               <p>But, an other kind of hearing there is, which hath alwayes accompanying <note place="margin">Faithfull hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> it, and inſeparably ioyned to it, faith in beléeuing that which is heard, and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in following that which is heard and beléeued. This hearing Moſes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth by ſaying, <hi>Yee ſhall heare him in all things, &amp;c.</hi> This hearing the voyce from heauen ſignifieth, giuing <hi>to heare him.</hi> This hearing our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 17. 5.</note> meaneth, <hi>He that is of God, hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 8. 47.</note> 
                  <hi>Gods words:</hi> and in an other place, <hi>My ſheepe heare my voyce, and I know them, and they followe mee.</hi> Thus A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 10. 27.</note> with faith and obedience heard the Lordes calling, when as hee depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gene.</hi> 12. 4.</note> out of his countrie. Gene. the xii. circumciſed himſelfe Geneſis the xvii. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gene.</hi> 17. 24.</note> and offered vp his onely ſonne Iſaac, as is recorded in the xxii. of Geneſis. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gene.</hi> 22. 10.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Thus the Prophets, Apoſtles, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyres, and all the faithfull heard Chriſt and his word when as neither pennury and lacke of neceſſaries, neither hatred
<pb facs="tcp:2853:26"/> and malice of men, neither pollicies and fetches of Sathan, neither tormentes and cruelties of Tyrantes, neither loſſe of life, and death it ſelfe coulde make them fal away from Ieſus Chriſt their Generall and captaine. It is written that Zeuſis ſo artificially painted a cluſter of grapes, that the birds flew to it, and picked at it, ſuppoſing it had ben a true naturall cluſter. Theſe ſilie poore byrdes were much deceiued: for they founde but painted grapes. Verilie, whoſoeuer ſhall heare the worde of God in this laſt ſenſe of hearing, and after the example of theſe hearers thus liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcribed by the holy Ghoſt, they ſhall finde that thoſe were, and themſelues are no peinted and counterfeit hearers, but verie true and effectuall hearers of this prophete Chriſte and his holy goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. They ſhal neuer deceiue their own ſelues, as did the birdes, and the vaine hearers do, <hi>but ſhall be bleſſed in their deed.</hi> Theſe hearers heare not Chriſte <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ia.</hi> 1. 22. 25.</note> and his word after their owne fancie &amp; liking, but in <hi>whatſoeuer he ſaith vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> as Peter here teacheth out of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.
<pb facs="tcp:2853:26"/> From the premiſſes &amp; matters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">A concluſion inferred vpon the diſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> true hearers.</note> ſpoken concerning true hearers of the worde, there groweth this conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: If none be true, fruitfull, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable hearers of the worde, either to their owne comforte and commoditie, or to God his honour &amp; glory, but ſuch, as heare with faith to beléeue in Chriſt, and his worde, and with obedience to followe Chriſte and his worde, then both idolatrous Papiſtes, and carnall proteſtantes (I will not once name A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſtes) are quit &amp; clean excluded out of the number of true, right, &amp; Chriſtian hearers. That Papiſts hear not Chriſt, &amp; his miniſters in this ſenſe of hearing, <note place="margin">Papiſtes are not true hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of Chriſts Goſpell.</note> that is, that they do not conforme their religion according to the doctrine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined in, and deliuered vnto them out of the worde of God, this is a matter ſo manifeſt, as all the faithfull do lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tablie and with griefe of hearte beholde the ſame. And, to giue themſelues (if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny be preſent) ſome taſte thereof, I will here ioyne battell and incounter with them, vſing that onely ſentence vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by our ſauiour in the ſourth of Iohn
<pb facs="tcp:2853:27"/> for the weapon, whereby I am ſure, &amp; I truſte the greateſt number preſent, <note place="margin">This alone ſentence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futeth and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>foundeth all poperie.</note> will confeſſe, that their whole religion or rather ſuperſtition, is wounded at the hearte, and ſtricken quite dead. For Chriſt in that place, talking with the woman of Samaria, telleth her y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>God is a ſpirit, and they that worſhippe him,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 4. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>muſt worſhippe him in ſpirit and truth.</hi> If we either looke on the whole body of their religion in groſſe, or diſmember and rippe the ſame into péeces, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde <note place="margin">Romiſh Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</note> euerie member, euerie ioynt, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie ſinewe, euerie veine, euerie ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie, euerie muſcle thereof, we ſhall be enforced to confeſſe, that, among them, there is no worſhipping of God in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite and trueth, but that all their wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe <note place="margin">A vew of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</note> and religion is corporall, exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and ceremoniall. Whoſoeuer ſhall with iudgement indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly view their <note place="margin">Meere cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall.</note> Religion, ſhall, in déede, perceiue it to be nothing elſe but an apiſhe and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeite imitation of the ceremoniall law. Hence they fetch their alters, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſtickes, Senſours, Perfumes, gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, Oblations, feſtiuall dayes, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne
<pb facs="tcp:2853:27"/> feaſts, difference of times, obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of meates, purifications, ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <note place="margin">An Apiſh imi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tation of the ceremoniall lawe.</note> and a number of the like nature. But as in all theſe and the reſidue, they haue no ſauour of ſpirite and trueth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gréeable either to gods nature diſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, or to the doctrin of the Goſpell deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered by Chriſt: ſo, in their following of the lawe, they doe ſhamfully halte. To giue yee an inſtance, they celebrate their maſſe at the Altar, but Chriſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred his laſte ſupper at a table. I <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mar.</hi> 14 18.</note> cannot denye but the lawe Ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all doeth commaunde Altars: howbeit ſuch Altars as ſhall be neither of hew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exo.</hi> 20. 25. 26</note> ſtone, nor haue any ſteppes ther vnto belonging. But the Romiſh Altars are of hewen ſtowne, and haue ſteppes, as is apparant in their Sinagogues: and <note place="margin">A tranſgreſſi-of the law ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remoniall.</note> as appereth by ſteppes yet remayning in many of our Temples, whereby ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther longing for that heatheniſh ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, or at the leaſt, colde affection to <note place="margin">Altar ſteppes in our Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</note> aduance true religion, is vndoubtedly ſignified. But, admitte their whole re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion were fully, in euery pointe, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondent and anſwerable to the law
<pb facs="tcp:2853:28"/> ceremoniall, what elſe ſhoulde that bée, but a full and flatte deniall of Chriſtes <note place="margin">The through obſeruation of the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial law, is a through de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall of Chriſt</note> death and paſſion, and of all the merits of the ſame? This is moſt ſubſtancially proued by our ſauiour Chriſt, and by his ſeruaunt Paule. Chriſt in that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſcripture before cited, ſaith that <hi>God is a ſpirit, and therefore they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 4. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>him, muſt worſhip him in ſpirit and trueth.</hi> In that place Spirit &amp; truth are oppoſed and ſet againſt the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the law, and the words of Chriſt ſo vttered to the woman of Samaria, <note place="margin">The effectual ſignification of thoſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des Spirite &amp; trueth.</note> importe thus much: Before the incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of me the then promiſed, and nowe perfourmed ſauiour, ye worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped God in ſhadowes, in figures, in ceremonies, in ſacrifices: but I béeing nowe come, who am the body of thoſe ſhaddowes, the trueth of thoſe figures, the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of thoſe ſacrifices, the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of thoſe ceremonies, nowe that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall worſhip ceaſeth, and ye muſte now worſhip God onely in ſpirite and trueth Here Paule ſaith in his Epiſtle to the Epheſians the ſecond chapter, <hi>He,</hi> that is Chriſt, <hi>is our peace, which hath</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2. 14.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2853:28"/> 
                  <hi>made of both one, and hath broken the ſtop of the partition wall: in abrogating through his fleſh, the hatred, that is, the law of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandementes, which ſtandeth in ordinaunces &amp;c.</hi> Again, writing vnto the Colloſſians, he hath the ſame in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Colloſſ.</hi> 2. 14.</note> and meaning. By both theſe places we are taught that Chriſt, by his death <note place="margin">Chriſts death ended and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brogated the Ceremoniall lawe.</note> and paſſion, hath abrogated &amp; taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the whole law of ceremonies: that place alſo in the laſt to the Hebrues is verie notable to this end and purpoſe, <hi>We haue an Altar, wherof they haue no</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>authoritie to eat, which ſerue in the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle.</hi> Whereby it is concluded, that ſuch as yet dwell in ceremonies of the law (much more of mens deuiſing) are ſtrangers fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ieſus Chriſt, who, by his one ſacrifice of his own body, once of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for al, hath cancelled the obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note place="margin">Obſeruers of the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall lawe. cut themſelu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> from Chriſt.</note> and handwriting of the ceremoniall lawe which was againſt vs. By theſe &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like teſtimonies of holy ſcripture, we ſée that ſuch as worſhip God either af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ceremoniall law of God, or after the ceremoniall deuiſes of men, do ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by deny the force of Chriſts death, yea
<pb facs="tcp:2853:29"/> they deny y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ieſus Chriſt is come in the fleſh. Of ſuch me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> S. Ioh. ſpeaketh in his firſt epiſtle, <hi>Euery ſpirit y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſeth not Ieſus Chriſt to be come in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh, is not of god: but this is the ſpirit of Antichriſt, &amp;c.</hi> I referre the néerer application of this ſentence to their own conſciences, praying the lord to giue them grace ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually to ſée, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortably to fele, &amp; faith fully to acknowledge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord Ieſus, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mightie force of his moſt effectuall death &amp; paſſion. Plinie in the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plin. li.</hi> 8. <hi>nat. hiſtor. cap.</hi> 27.</note> eight booke of his naturall hiſtorie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Swallowes vſe to make the blind &amp; ſoare eyes of their yong ones to ſée, by rubbing the ſame w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> an herbe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Celandine, ſo named, ſome ſay, of <note place="margin">Celandine.</note> the ſwallowes firſt finders, and ſuch v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers therof: ſome ſay, <hi>quia confert caeleſtia dona,</hi> bicauſe it hath heauenly vertues. The papiſts eyes are very ſore &amp; blind, <note place="margin">The papiſtes eyes ſore and blind.</note> they cannot abide to looke vppon Ieſus Chriſt the glorious ſonne of God thus brightly ſhining amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt vs. The Lord in his mercie giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his heauenly <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landine,</hi> I mean his holy ſpirit, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with their blind eyes may bee opened,
<pb facs="tcp:2853:29"/> their darke vnderſtanding lightened, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>A view of the principal me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of their and our religi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on together. Only God to be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped. Deu.</hi> 10. 20. 6 19. <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. 10 <hi>Only God to be praied vnto Pſal.</hi> 50. 15. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 9. <hi>We muſt pray with the hart. Eſa.</hi> 29. 13. <hi>Mat.</hi> 15. 8. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 15. <hi>Faith onely iuſtifieth. Gen.</hi> 15. 6. <hi>Hab.</hi> 2. 4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 1. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 16. <hi>Two Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Mat.</hi> 28. 19. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. 26. <hi>The ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments muſt be admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping to chriſts inſtitution.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 23</note> their hard harts mollified &amp; ſoftened. If as in groſſe we haue viewed the whole bodie of their religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo nowe we looke vppon the ſame by piece meale, ſhal we therein finde any ſpirite and truth? ſhal we not finde it altogether deuoid of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite and trueth, and wholy corporall, carnall, and earthly? Spirite and truth will haue the Lord God alone worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped and ſerued: they worſhip and ſerue Saintes, creatures, Reliques, bootes, buſkins, nailes, &amp;c. Spirit &amp; trueth will haue God alone to be prayed vnto: they pray to Saintes, to creatures, to Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, to ſtockes and ſtones. Spirite and trueth will haue our praiers procéede from an vnderſtanding hart: they teach &amp; charge the people to pray in a ſtrange and vnknowen language. Spirite and trueth will haue vs fréely iuſtified by faith in Chriſt, they ioyne mans merits purchaſers with the pretious bloude of Chriſt. Spirite and truth wil haue but two Sacramentes, to wit Baptiſme, and the Lords ſupper: they adde to theſe two, fiue moe of their owne coyning, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:2853:30"/> ſo will haue ſeuen ſacraments. Spirite and truth willeth vs ſimplie to admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the Sacramentes according to the Lords holy inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: they haue added, altred, deminiſhed, augmented, as them ſelues luſted. To baptiſm they haue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded oyle, creame, ſpittle, croſſings, bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing by women, baptizing before the birth of the childe, a tying of ſaluation vnto baptiſme. To the Lord his ſupper they haue added, Altars, candleſtickes, Tapers, pixe, Tranſubſtantiatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, reſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, circumgeſtation and carrying about of the Sacrament. &amp;c. Spirite and trueth willeth vs to heare chriſt <hi>In al things whatſoeuer he ſhal ſay</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chriſt muſt be h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rd in all thinges. Deut</hi> 18 22. <hi>Mat.</hi> 17 5. <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e holy ſcripture con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teineth al thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges neceſſarie to ſaluation. Deu.</hi> 4. 6. <hi>Lu.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 29. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>vnto vs,</hi> Wherby we are throughly aſſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red that all things neceſſarily required vnto our ſaluation are conteined in the ſacred ſcriptures: but they ground vpon reuelatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, apparitions, vnwritten ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, lying myracles, and moſt abſurd fables. Thus I might (right welbelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the Lord) examine the huge mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous maſſe of all their religion, and nether in it al generally, nor in any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular part thereof finde any ſpirit and
<pb facs="tcp:2853:30"/> trueth, but only that, which is earthly, corporal, carnal and fleſhlie. If it be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied that the papiſts are learned men, antient men, wiſe men, &amp; of long expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, <note place="margin">An obiection that the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts are lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. &amp;c.</note> and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> therfore it is maruel they ſhold ſo groſly be deceiued, that wheras god being a ſpirit, &amp; therfore wil be wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhipped in ſpirit and truth, they haue yet in al their ſeruice &amp; worſhip no ſpirit &amp; truth. The ſcribes &amp; Phariſes were as <note place="margin">Anſwere to the ſame.</note> ancient, wiſe, learned, and expert as the papiſts, &amp; yet they perſecuted &amp; crucified Chriſte, and with all violence oppoſed &amp; ſet themſelues againſt his goſpell. In the eleuenth of Matth. Chriſt breaketh out into theſe words, <hi>I giue thee thanks, O father, Lord of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; earth, bicauſe thou haſt hid theſe things from the wiſe</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 11. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>and men of vnderſtanding, and haſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened them to babes. It is ſo, O father, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thy good pleaſure was ſuch.</hi> This our heauenly Scholemaſter here tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> true religion, right knowledge of the worde, and a thorough féeling of Chriſt, are not tied to the Vniuerſities, to great Doctours, to gray heads, but that the Lord God beſtoweth theſe good
<pb facs="tcp:2853:31"/> giftes fréely, in what place ſoeuer, at what time ſoeuer, and vpon whome ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioan.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 8.</note> he pleaſeth.</p>
               <p>And, verily, as the Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes framed to themſelues certeine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices to kéep them from Chriſt, as that he was but the ſonne of a carpenter, kept companie with ſinners, abounded not with worldly iolitie in princely ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. 55. <hi>Mar.</hi> 2. 16</note> ſo, for all the world, do our Papiſts deuiſe means to hinder them from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vnto the ſame Chriſt. We can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, ſay they, away with his newe doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, <note place="margin">The fond ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments of ignorant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued ſoules.</note> (for ſo they ſclanderouſly call the auntient trueth of God his worde) all is new plaine Dunſtable, the ſeruice is in the vulgare toung, euerie bodie may vnderſtand it, the edifying of the ſoul is now altogether cared for, there is now <note place="margin">A liuely and true picture of the Popiſh maſking reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</note> in our Church no pleaſing and deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of our outward ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces. In our maſſe time (the verie name whereof comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth our hart) our ſeruice was in a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned language, it was not vnderſtanded of the common ſorte, wee prayed to the bleſſed Saintes in heauen, we knéeled to trim painted images, our churches
<pb facs="tcp:2853:31"/> were gailie decked, there was ringing, <note place="margin">Can ye here finde any ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite and truth?</note> ſinging, ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cing, piping, glittering copes, ſiluer Cenſours, golden Croſſes, mitred fathers, encloiſtred brethren, religious Siſters, Chriſtening of belles, hollow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of fontes, créeping to the croſſe, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering of egges, ſprinkling of holy wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, dealing of holy bred, auriculer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, good ſporte on Alhallon night, lighting of tapers, making merrie, going on pilgrimage, pardoning of ſin for a litle monie, we liued as we luſted, Prieſtes were good fellowes, adulterie <note place="margin">The belly rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of carnall and ſenſleſſe people.</note> was borne withall, bread was bigger, ale was ſtronger, béefe more plentifull, troutes fatter and better, all thinges cheaper, xxiiij. egges for a penie. Nowe all theſe ar gone, euerie childe can now vnderſtand the ſeruice, Images are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden, <note place="margin">Fowle faultes I promiſe you</note> God is now worſhipped in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite &amp; truth, euery bodie is now ſkilfull <note place="margin">But Chriſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ye were in the name of the Father &amp;c. and therefore tied not to the maſſe, but to the worſhipping of God.</note> in the ſcriptures, the knowledge of the Catechiſme, and abilitie to yelde an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of our faith is looked for and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded. We were borne and chriſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Maſſe time, our forefathers were of that ſtamp, we wil none of this
<pb facs="tcp:2853:32"/> new doctrine. Euen ſo the Iews, when they were deliuered from Idolatrie, &amp; reſtored vnto the true knowledge and worſhip of God, many of them miſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that eſtate (as Ieremie witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth) cried out againſt him in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. <hi>We will not heare the worde that</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier.</hi> 44. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>thou ſpeakeſt vnto vs in the name of the Lorde, but we will doe euery thing that ſhal proceed from our own mouth, as to burne incenſe to the queene of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, to offer vp drink offerings vnto her as both we haue done, &amp; our fathers, &amp; our kings and princes in the Citie of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da, and in the ſtreates of Ieruſalem: For then had wee plentie of victualles, and were well, and felt none euill. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe, deare brethren, theſe are the reaſons which ſtoppe manie Papiſtes eares from hearkening to this Prophet Ieſus Chriſt. Ye heare and ſée the vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of theſe reaſons, and howe farre they are from any reaſon. They néede no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>futation, very children haue them in deriſion, and laugh them to ſcorne.</p>
               <p>Chriſoſtom moſt notably compareth the gentiles or heathen people to chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,
<pb facs="tcp:2853:32"/> which compariſon will ſerue now verie fitlie, if, in ſtéede of his heathen men, we vnderſtand our heatheniſh pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts. Saieth Chriſoſtom, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t pueri nulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us vtilitatis curam ſuſcipiunt. &amp;c. As chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren haue no regarde of any profite, ſo the gentiles are deſirous to play conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chriſoſt. in.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor. Hom.</hi> 4.</note> 
                  <hi>and they lye flatte vppon the ground, and are in loue with baſe things. When we often talke of neceſſarie mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, children vnderſtand not our talke, but fall a laughing: Euen ſo the gentiles, when wee ſpeake of the kingdome of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Chryſoſtom proueth the Gentiles to be children.</note> 
                  <hi>heauen, they doe nothing but laugh. And as out of a childes mouth there iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſueth much ſpitle, which nowe and then marreth both meate and drinke: ſo the wordes, which come out of the gentiles mouthes, are vaine and vile: and, if thou ſet needfull food before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they vexe thee with curſed ſpeches, &amp; wiſh it to be taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, moreouer, when they ſee a theefe goe into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe, and ſteale away the furniture thereof, they doe not onely not reuenge, but they ſmile &amp; look pleaſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly on him: but if you take awai their ſuckling box, or rattle, or</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2853:33"/> 
                  <hi>any ſuch like childiſhe bable, then they take that heauily, they are grieued, they teare them ſelues, they ſtampe vpon the pauement. So do the gentils, when they ſee the diuell ſteale away all they haue, both their inheritance, or liuelihod, &amp; what ſoeuer thinges are neceſſarie for their ſoules health, they laugh, and, as if he were their friend, they go out to meet him. But if any man lay hand vpon their poſſeſſions, riches, and ſuch like thinges, then they mourne, and pull themſelues a peeces.</hi> This, as I tolde ye, is golden mouthed Chriſoſtoms excellent compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, wherin he notably proueth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then men to be children &amp; babes, when as they made ſuch great reckoning of vaine tranſitorie thinges, and yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted and contemned Chriſt Ieſus. If ye <note place="margin">The more then childiſh folly of our Popiſh babes.</note> vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d our vngentle Papiſts for his gentiles, ye ſhall, as it were in a glaſſe, clearely behold the mad and more then childiſh follie of our Romaniſtes, who ſo eſtéeme their Croſſes, Altars, ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, holy water, Copes, Images, and ſuche like ſuperſtitious toyes, as, in the mean time, they make none account
<pb facs="tcp:2853:33"/> of worſhipping God in ſpirit and truth, or to heare Chriſt and his goſpell fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully: and therefore the concluſion is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and true, That Papiſtes are not true hearers of the worde of God.</p>
               <p>Nowe, touching carnall proteſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes <note place="margin">That carnall proteſtantes are no true hearers of the worde.</note> to proue them no true heares of god his worde, is a matter of no great diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie and hardneſſe, but may eaſily be accompliſhed and brought to paſſe by the former diſcription of true and effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall hearers. For in true hearers two thinges are neceſſarily required, the <note place="margin">The worde ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be effec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tually heard without faith &amp; obedience Obedience the fruit of faith.</note> one, faith in beléeuing: the other, obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in following. Faith is the trée, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience is the fruit whereby faith may be diſcerned and knowen. Let vs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by obedience (as it were by an eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peciall good bloud hound) trace out the faith of theſe carnall profeſſours: and ſo ſhall we find in them no ſound faith, but a pretended faith: no liuely iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faith, but a dead condemned faith, whereof S. Iames ſpeaketh in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iam.</hi> 2. 20.</note> chapter of his epiſtle.</p>
               <p>Obedience is an heartie ſubmiſſion, <note place="margin">What obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is.</note> and through conformation of our ſelues
<pb facs="tcp:2853:34"/> to that which the Lorde our God hath preſcribed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſcripturs, either for the worſhip &amp; ſeruice of him, or for our behauiour towardes men. If we looke for this obedience, when, or how ſhall we finde it in theſe maner of men? For one ſort of theſe men wil go no further <note place="margin">One ſorte of counterfeit Chriſtians de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed.</note> in religion, then they may liue in all worldes, pleaſe euerie prince, ſerue eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie turne, and ſuſteyne neither loſſe nor lacke, nor any kinde of trouble or diſpleaſure. If theſe good fellowes méet with Papiſtes, they reſiſt not: if with Atheiſtes, they ſtriue not: if with tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porizers and ſeruers of time, their hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours are fedde: if with zelous &amp; true Chriſtians, they become key colde, and yet hollowe pretenders of loue and good will to the Goſpell. Theſe honeſt men can w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> the Camelio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſforme the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues into euery colour: w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their breath they <note place="margin">Theſe applye themſelues to liue in all worldes, ſaue in the world to come.</note> can (as is in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fable) make warme their handes, and make colde their pottage. And, although by reaſon of the ſtate and time preſent, they will bee accounted proteſtantes: yet, if yee marke it, they cheriſh none, truſt none, kéepe compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie
<pb facs="tcp:2853:34"/> and delight heartely in none, but ſuch as are notorious and knowne Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes. Aeſope felleth a pretie tale of an huſband man, who ſéeing his cornefeld ſpoiled with Géeſe and Cranes, did therefore ſet a ſnare for them, and at length tooke them both, and a ſtorke with them. The ſtorke fearing death vehementely, and like an Orator <note place="margin">The ſtorke taken in ill company, ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteineth like puniſhment with them.</note> pleaded her owne cauſe, declaringe her innocencie, her excellencie aboue other birdes, her ſingular care ouer her aged parentes, and vpon theſe conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, praied to be ſet at libertie. The huſbandman more regarding his loſſe of corne, then the Storkes glorious wordes, ſaide vnto her, As I haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the in euill companie, ſo thou ſhalt alſo die with them. In like manner, when the Lorde Ieſus, that heauenly huſbandman, ſhall call theſe carnall <note place="margin">The ſtate of ſuch as are companions with profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed enemies of Chriſt.</note> wretches to an accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for their treading vnder féete and ſpoyling the holy ſéede of his eternal word co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually caſt out &amp; ſowen among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for their drawing the yoke with infidels, &amp; ioyning with
<pb facs="tcp:2853:35"/> the ſworne enemies of the Goſpell, let them bee aſſured, that no wordly polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie, no humane reaſon, no fine deuice, no forged excuſe ſhall be accepted: but as they haue kept companie with thoſe wicked ones moſt offenſiuely: ſo, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpéedie repentance, they ſhall periſh with them euerlaſtingly. The good pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete and noble Kinge Dauid, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what a great let and hinderaunce the companie of the wicked is, and how it entiſeth men from the zealous and heartie ſeruing of the Lorde, doth with great zeale, and in moſt vehement ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner breake out into theſe words, <hi>Away from mee, ye wicked, for I will keep the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dauids deteſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of wicked companie Pſa.</hi> 119. 115.</note> 
                  <hi>commaundementes of my God.</hi> And being taught by the holy Ghoſt what a good prouocation it is to godlineſſe, to be alwayes conuerſant &amp; familier with the faithfull and godlie, the ſame Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid in moſte ioyfull manner, vttereth theſe wordes in the ſixtéenth Pſalme, <hi>All my delight is vpon the Saintes that</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dauids hearty delight in go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie. Pſal.</hi> 16. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>are in the earth, and ſuch as excel in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue.</hi> But the worlde doeth now take a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie courſe. For the Saints of God
<pb facs="tcp:2853:35"/> are not eſteemed, their companie not regarded, the name of ſaintes is derided <note place="margin">The worlde is drowned with the carnall loue of vaine companions.</note> and laughed to ſcorne. All delight is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in Italianate heades, diſcourſing tonges, &amp; merie conceited companions. Epicures, toſſepottes, riotous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, leude talkers, theſe growe nowe a dayes, vnto greate credit. But true Chriſtians carefully endeuouring to ſhewe themſelues conformable to their profeſſion of Chriſt, are nothing, or ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie little, and a verie few, eſtéemed &amp; ſet by. But this is not to be woondered at: <note place="margin">No meruell if gods children be contemned whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his word is ſo diſpiſed.</note> for the verie word of God and the true preaching thereof is now ſo contemned and diſpiſed, ſo croſſed, and maliciouſly and of ſet purpoſe ouer wharted, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery vaine fidler, and vagabound Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per <note place="margin">Dancing in many places more eſtemed then prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching.</note> in the country doth carrie away the vnthankefull people, euen vppon the Lorde his holy Saboth dayes, and other times dedicated to his ſeruice, and that from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hearing of Gods holy worde and worſhipping of him, vnto <note place="margin">The effectes of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly vſed dancinges.</note> carnall, vnchriſtian, and filthy daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinges, the verie nource of carnal talke, of horrible blaſphemie, of damnable for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nication,
<pb facs="tcp:2853:36"/> of pride, of theft, of diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to God, to prince, to parentes, to all ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perious. The filthines of this vſuall dancing moued the auncient fathers of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <note place="margin">The auncient fathers ſharpe inuectiues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing.</note> and ſharpely to inueigh againſte it in their dayes, but what woulde they haue done, if they had liued in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent age? Chriſoſtome ſaith, <hi>vbi ſaltus laſciuus, ibi diabolus certe adeſt,</hi> where <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chriſoſt. in Mat.</hi> 14. <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>9.</note> wanton dauncing is vſed, there the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel is certenly preſent. And in the ſame homilie, they that daunce nowe a days, deſire not that Iohn ſhould bee headed, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoules of ſuch as are in their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany ſhould be deſtroied. Likewiſe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin vpon the third pſalme ſaith, <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerua diem Sabbati, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> carnaliter, &amp;c.</hi> that <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſtine in Pſal.</hi> 3.</note> is, kéepe the Saboth day, not carnally, not with Iewiſhe vanities, whiche a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe and prophane their reſt, &amp; make it a cauſe of lendeneſſe. Againe, ſaith Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine, ſpeaking of the reſt vppon the Saboth day, <hi>Non dico vt delitteris, quem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admodum Iudaei ſolent. Melius est enim to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to die fodere, quàm ſaltare die Sabbati,</hi> my meaning is not (ſaith Auguſtine) that thou ſhouldeſt ſpende the Saboth daye
<pb facs="tcp:2853:36"/> vainely, as the Iewes vſe to doe. For it is better to digge and delue all the day, then to daunce vpon the Saboth daye. If we had grace, that one exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of the murdering of innocent Iohn Baptiſt, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 14. 6. 10</note> by occaſion of wanton dauncing, might ſet before our eyes how daungerous a matter it is to frequent the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing places. And how ſtreightly the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mortification and newneſſe of life com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded. Rom.</hi> 6. <hi>a.</hi> 4. 2. <hi>Cor</hi> 4. 10. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 16. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 28. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. 36. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 5. 11.</note> ghoſt doth commaund mortification, ſubduing of our wanton affections, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe in thought, wordes, workes, eyes, tongues, generally and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, this ye haue learned by the often hearinge and readinge of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: and therefore ye cannot be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, but muſt néedes knowe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe howe vnſéemely, how vnchriſtian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, how diſpleaſant to God, and offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue to good men the accuſtomed daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of men &amp; women vppon the dayes before named is, yea, and that their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of dancing may verie well &amp; truely <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. ad frat. in Eremo. Ier.</hi> 33.</note> be called (as Auguſtin calleth it) <hi>a flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Diuell, a ſweete poyſon, a ſinfull pleaſure, or a pleaſaunt ſinne.</hi> And ſo far are thoy from hope to reformo this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
<pb facs="tcp:2853:37"/> dancing, as we lamentably ſee <note place="margin">Vanitie better countenanced then veritie.</note> many placed in authoritie to like well thereof, and rather maintaine irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous dancers, then eſtéeme and hearken vnto the iuſt complaint of godlie prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, which openly in ſermons, priuat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by ſupplications, &amp; euery waye haue laboured for the ſuppreſſing of this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table cauſe of many miſcheuous incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniences. It is déepely layed to our charge, that we ſpeake againſt al man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of recreations. And yet it is well <note place="margin">We are vniuſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly accuſed to diſlike all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creations.</note> knowen that we like and vſe recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. In déed we ſay this, that both wée, and all that feare the Lorde, muſte not alone in earneſt and weightie affaires, but alſo in our verie ſportes and mirth, and paſtimes, ſéeke the glorie of god, by endeuouring to put of the olde man of <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 31.</note> ſinne, and to ſhewe foorth liuely fruites of true regeneration: that whatſoeuer we ſay or doe, it may thereby appeare <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. 11.</note> we haue béene baptiſed as with water, ſo likwiſe <hi>with the holy ghoſt and fire,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">What it is to bee baptiſed with fire &amp; the holy Ghoſt.</note> that is inwardly and effectually: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they can neuer truely and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably aſſure themſelues, which let looſe
<pb facs="tcp:2853:37"/> the bridle of their affections, and, as it were, ſell their bodies and ſoules to riotous, vnchaſte, and vngodly daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, and ſuch other carnall delightes, ſo horribly frequented by the common ſort of people in many places of this Realme, to the fruſtrating of oure la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, the hinderance of the goſpell, the increaſe of wickedneſſe, &amp; therfore to the greate ioy of Sathan and all his adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents. The Lord, in mercie, giue ſuche <note place="margin">A moſt need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full prayer.</note> ſtrength and courage to all magiſtrats, that ſetting a ſide frendſhip, reſpect of gaine, care to be popular, and all earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſiderations, they may throughly &amp; friendly ioyne their temporall ſworde with the woorde of God, whiche is the ſworde of the ſpirite, for the cutting <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ephe.</hi> 6. 17.</note> downe of what ſoeuer thinges ſhall be founde any manner of impediment and let to the inlarging of Chriſtes king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. And the ſame Lord turne the fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <note place="margin">The damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny Godleſſe people.</note> harts of many people, that wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as now they bende themſelues to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo much, as to erect and ſet vp va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, and to vexe, moleſt, and grieue the heartes, and diſcredite, ſlaunder,
<pb facs="tcp:2853:38"/> and ſtain the names euen of their lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned &amp; godly teachers: they may ſpéedily ſhew harty repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; become obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t hearers &amp; followers of God &amp; his word. And as in the countrie minſtrels thus ſeduce &amp; bewitch the people, ſo it hath bene ſayd (I truſt it be reformed) that <note place="margin">Plaiers about London.</note> vaine plaiers haue had about this citie of London farre greater audience, then true preachers. This vniuerſal lothing of Chriſtes holy goſpell doth prognoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticate a famine, <hi>not of bread and water</hi> that is, not of corporall foode: but (as the Prophet ſayth) a famine of <hi>hearing the worde of the Lorde.</hi> It woulde pearce <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Amos.</hi> 8. 11.</note> through our heartes with intollerable griefe to féele our ſelues, and ſée our children periſh with wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of bodily ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. This was the miſerable conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note place="margin">What the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Gods word doth foretell.</note> and eſtate of the wicked Iewes at the finall deſtruction of that moſte fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Ieruſalem. Then the Parentes ſawe the pitifull famine and ſtaruing of their children, the children of their Parentes, one, of an other. Almoſt all <note place="margin">The famin at the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</note> things they layd hands vppon (though moſt vnnatural) thei vſed as meat. The
<pb facs="tcp:2853:38"/> tender hearted mother ſpared not with her own hands to ſlea her own innocent <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioſeph. de bello Iudaico lib.</hi> 7. <hi>Cap.</hi> 8.</note> and natural child, and with his vnplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fleſh, to nouriſh her famiſhing body, &amp; to ſtay her vnreaſonable hungrie ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite. Verilie, this is a ſorrowful nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But another maner of griefe ſhal the famine of God his word bring with <note place="margin">The effect of the ſpirituall famin of god his word.</note> it: when as, by means therof manie fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and mothers with their children, manie maiſters with their ſeruaunts, many gouernours with their people, ſhall pine away, and periſh euerlaſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the eternal death of body &amp; ſoul.</p>
               <p>This will be a dolefull daunce, and to this ende (without heartie and preſent <note place="margin">A dolefull daunce.</note> amendement) the vſuall contemptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous dauncing, the deſpiſing of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, the ſinnefull delightes, the diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred life of the vngodly, the profanatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of holy dayes, the loue of playing, the lothing and hatred of preaching, will bring our happie and golden dayes, if God bee not verie mercifull to vs. Thus haue ye heard that, in theſe firſt ſort of carnall Proteſtantes, there can be found no obedience, and therfore no
<pb facs="tcp:2853:39"/> liuely faith, and ſo conſequently, they are no fruitfull hearers of the worde.</p>
               <p>Another ſort of lippe prefeſſours are zealous in religion, feruentlie bente a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <note place="margin">Another kind of carnall Chriſtians.</note> poperie, great talkers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, pretenders of much honeſtie: but yet among them ye ſhall finde vnmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull vſurers, couetous oppreſſours, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame dealers in worldly thinges, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiable cormorantes, filthie Epicures: <note place="margin">Figge treers with leaues onely.</note> theſe men wil vſe faire words, but haue foule hearts, they will ſweare, and yet lie: they make a ſhew of ſimplicitie, and for all that, are full of deceipt: they can <note place="margin">Theſe means are gluttony, tipling, vile companie, vain talk. &amp;c.</note> talke of mortification, &amp; yet vſe meanes (as it were with bellowes) to blowe vp and kindle the fire of carnall conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The caſe of theſe men are moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable. Better they had neuer knowen <note place="margin">The miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble eſtate of theſe men.</note> the worde of God. Better they had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer bene borne. Better a milſtone had ben ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged about thier neckes then ſo to haue offended Chriſts litle ones. Their owne knowledge of the word, and yet diſobedience to the worde pronounceth ſentence of iuſt condemnation againſt
<pb facs="tcp:2853:39"/> them. Theſe are ſuch as Chriſt ſpeaketh <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 7. 21.</note> of, <hi>Not euerie one that ſaieth vnto mee, Lord, Lorde, ſhall enter into the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. &amp;c.</hi> Theſe are fooliſh lookers into <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iam.</hi> 1. 22.</note> the glaſſe of God his worde: <hi>hearers on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, deceiuing their owne ſelues.</hi> Theſe are cloudes without water, carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iude.</hi> 12.</note> of windes, corrupt trées and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fruite; Theſe are <hi>chaffe whiche the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal,</hi> 1 4.</note> 
                  <hi>winde driueth away.</hi> Yea, that chaffe, which Chriſt will burne with vnquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chable <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. 12.</note> fire. Theſe are figge trées which <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 21. 19.</note> beare leaues only, &amp; no fruite, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vnable to endure y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of chriſt, In the ſeconde booke of Samuell it is written that King Dauid ſent ſome of <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 10. 2 3. 4, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> his ſeruants to comfort Hanun king of the Ammonites lamenting for his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers deth. But Hanun, perſwaded by <note place="margin">Euill counſel.</note> his noble men, that Dauids ſeruantes came rather as eſpialles, then as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forters, he vſed them moſt villanouſly: he ſhaued off the halfe of their beardes, <note place="margin">Ingratitude.</note> cut of their garments in the middle, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to their buttockes, and ſent them away. Theſe carnall hearers, both theſe ſortes, and all other the like, they
<pb facs="tcp:2853:40"/> offer more villanie to themſelues, then Hanun did to Dauids ſeruauntes. For that done to Dauids men, was but temporall, this they do to them ſelues, is eternal: the halfe of their berds were ſhauen of, theſe doe what they canne to <note place="margin">What vilani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es all carnall hearers do to themſelues.</note> raze their whole names out of the booke of life: they had but part of their bodily garmentes defaced, theſe ſéeke to make themſelues vtterly naked and deſtitute of Chriſtes righteouſneſſe, that ſpirituall garment, whiche coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the ſinns of the faithful: they were ſent out of the preſence but of an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt and earthly prince: theſe ſhall wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie depart from the ſight of Chriſte that righteous and heauenly King.</p>
               <p>For, as it is ſayde in the laſt parte concerning the puniſhment whiche ſhall be executed vppon all diſobedient hearers.</p>
               <p>33. <hi>Euery perſon which ſhall not heare that Prophet, ſhall bee deſtroyed</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The fourth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd laſt part.</note> 
                  <hi>out of the people.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2853:40"/>
               <p> O miſerable men which thus vnkindly and vnthankfully refuſe to heare, and <note place="margin">The puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient and carnal hearers</note> come vnto this Ieſus Chriſte, whiche calleth them, bountifully, by benefites: louingly, by promiſes: ſharpely, by threatninges: generally, together: par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 5. 6. 7.</note> a ſunder: by ſignes, from <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 11. 28.</note> Heauen: by monſters, vppon earth: by <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 21. 43. <hi>Chriſt his ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of calling vs.</hi>
                  </note> puniſhing, iuſtly: by pardoning, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully: by his worde, continually. And yet theſe wicked men make greater reckoning of buying farmes, of trying Oxen, of marying, wiues, of their very hogges, and vileſt thinges, yea, of their <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lu.</hi> 14. 18. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> carnall affections, and vaineſt delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 8. 34.</note> then of ſaluation offered vnto them by Ieſus Chriſte. Wherefore, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde the price of their diſobedience, <hi>they ſhall be deſtroyed, or rooted out of the people:</hi> euerlaſting deſtruction re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth as a moſte bitter cuppe for them to drinke off.</p>
               <p>Marke this, ye obſtinate Papiſtes, <note place="margin">An exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to papiſts</note> which, like the deafe adder, ſtoppe your eares againſt the charmer, charme he neuer ſo wiſely. Marke this, ye car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>8. 4. <hi>To vaine proteſtants.</hi>
                  </note> hearers and talkers of the worde,
<pb facs="tcp:2853:41"/> which make the goſpell a cloake for your iniquities, and outwardly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it without any inwarde féeling of it, or outward co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forming of your ſelues vnto it. Oh, repent, repent, and betimes <note place="margin">To both pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes and counterfeit Chriſtians.</note> repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, leaſt Ieſus Chriſt, which now of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth himſelfe to be your louing Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, leaſt he, I ſay, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e as a terrible, but yet a moſt righteous iudge, &amp; allot vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter darkneſſe for your inheritance, and commaund ye to depart into euerlaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting fire prepared for the diuell and his <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math</hi> 25. 41.</note> angelles: whiche is here ſignified by theſe wordes, <hi>ſhall be deſtroyed out of the people.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ordinarie allowaunce of time, I perceiue, is ſpent: and therefore I muſt, contrarie to my purpoſe, omitte many thinges, whereof I determined to ſpeak in this laſte parte. Onely I will, in briefe manner, call vnto your good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, the ſumme &amp; effect of that which hath bene now ſpoken, and ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this my plaine diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>Ye haue heard (good Chriſtians) in the firſt part, that the Lorde God ſhall <note place="margin">Reherſall of the premiſſes.</note> raiſe vp this Prophet, and therefore,
<pb facs="tcp:2853:41"/> that the Lorde is authour of the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of his holy word and ſacraments. In this place ye had deliuered to your good conſiderations theſe thrée thinges concerninge eccleſiaſticall miniſters, The care to be vſed in the election and appointing miniſters: The conſcience and abilitie of miniſters: The dignitie and worthineſſe of ſuch miniſters.</p>
               <p>In the ſeconde parte it was declared what manner of Prophete was vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danded by this Prophete. To this end thrée ſortes of Prophetes were menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, and it was concluded that this prophete repreſenteth all ſuch, as haue béene, are, and ſhall be bleſſed with abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie and giftes faithfully and diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to interprete, and fruitefully and effectually to apply his holy worde. Here yee were certified, as alſo in the firſt part, that this prophet doth ſignifie both Chriſt, and all the true miniſters of his worde: and alſo, that God, of his mercie and goodneſſe, will neuer leaue his Church millitant here vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, altogither deſtitute of ſincere preachers of his word: by which word the Church
<pb facs="tcp:2853:42"/> muſt be directed and gouerned.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, I ſhewed what obedient eare muſt be giuen to this prophete, <hi>Ye ſhall heare him in all thinges. &amp;c.</hi> Vpon occaſion directly offered by theſe words I ſpake of two kindes of hearing the word of God, the one outward and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable, the other inwarde and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall. To this latter kind of hearing ye were doen to vnderſtande that faith and obedience are requiſit and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and that for want of this faith and obedience, neither Papiſtes, nor car-carnall Proteſtantes can be iuſtly rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened in the number of true hearers.</p>
               <p>And therefore (as was noted in the laſt member) all theſe vaine hearers, of what ſort ſoeuer they be, ſhal be ſeuere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly puniſhed, and that with an euerlaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting puniſhment, they <hi>ſhall be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of the people.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now (dearly beloued in the Lord) ſith all hearers of the holy word of God are <note place="margin">What is to be done when we haue heard the word prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched.</note> eyther vaine and fruitleſſe hearers to their condemnation: or true and fruite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hearers to their ſaluation: it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore behoueth vs when we haue heard
<pb facs="tcp:2853:42"/> the worde, to enter into our owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, <note place="margin">How we ſhall knowe whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we heare it profitably, or otherwiſe.</note> and ſtreightly examine our ſelues how we haue heard the ſame. If we heare it onely outwardly, for feare, for fauour, for faſhion, if wee in this glaſſe doe beholde the deformities of our bodies and ſoules, and be careleſſe to reforme them: if we heare vſurie, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, <note place="margin">The effect of vain hearing.</note> inſatiable gréedineſſe of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thinges, Pride, Epicuriſme, wicked company, blaſphemie, contempt of gods worde, diſobedience to his lawes, adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie, fornication, Idolatrie, ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, papeſtry, witcheraft, charming, idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in our ſeuerall vocations, malice towardes our brethren, deceitfull dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, if we heare theſe &amp; other vices con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to hel fire by the word of God, and yet vſe them, delight in them, and let them be ſtill familiarly acquainted with vs, verily, verily, then this wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full &amp; lamentable caſe muſt of neceſſity followe, we deceiue our own ſelues, we are diſobedient hearers, our faith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> deade faith, our houſe builded vppon the ſands, the fal thereof ſhall be great, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> left hand is alloted, eternall torments
<pb facs="tcp:2853:43"/> appointed. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>The effect of fruitefull hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. Ia.</hi> 2. 18. <hi>&amp;c. Matth.</hi> 7 24. <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. 33. <hi>Marc.</hi> 3. 35.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But, if we heare with faith to beléeue, and obedience to followe, then, beholde, our moſt ioyful eſtate, our faith is liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and iuſtifieth: our houſe is ſtedfaſt, and ſtandeth: the right hand ſhall be our place, ioy ſhal be out portion: we ſhalbe bleſſed, we ſhal be the ſpiritual kinſfolk of our ſauiour, the kingdom of heauen, the fulneſſe of glorie ſhall be giuen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs through our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte the king of glory, to whome with his father, and the holy ghoſt, thrée perſons &amp; one immortall, inuiſible, and almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God let vs yelde all honour, power, glorie, and dominion both nowe and for euer. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 5. 17.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <hi>Be not vnwiſe, but vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what the will of the Lord is.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by Henrie Middleton for George Byſhop.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2853:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
